Tell your daughters of this year,
أخبري بناتك القادمات في هذا العام،
how we woke needing coffee
كيف أصبحنا في حاجة للقهوة
but discovered instead cadavers strewn about our morning papers,
وبدلاً من ذلك، اكتشفنا الجثث المنثورة عن أوراقنا الصباحية،
waterlogged facsimiles of our sisters, spouses, small children.
رسائل الفاكس غمرتها المياه لأخواتنا وأزواجنا وأطفالنا الصغار.
Say to your baby of this year when she asks, as she certainly should,
أخبري طفلتك القادمة هذا العام عندما تسألك، وستفعل حتماً،
tell her it was too late coming.
أنه فات أوان المجيء.
Admit even in the year we leased freedom, we didn't own it outright.
اعترفي بأنه في العام الذي استأجرنا فيه حريتنا لم نمتلكها بالتمام.
There were still laws for every way we used our privates
لم تزل هناك قوانين لكل طريقة مارسنا فيه خصوصياتنا
while they pawed at the soft folds of us,
بينما تنشب أظفارها في كل ثنياتنا الرقيقة،
grabbed with no concern for consent,
تأسرنا غير عابئة بالقبول،
no laws made for the men that enforced them.
لم تصنع القوانين لصالح الرجال.
We were trained to dodge,
لقد نشأنا على المراوغة،
to wait, to cower and cover,
والانتظار، والانكماش والتدثر،
to wait more, still, wait.
أن يدوم الانتظار أكثر، ننتظر.
We were told to be silent.
أُمرنا أن نصمت.
But speak to your girls of this wartime,
ولكن أخبري بناتك بوقت الحرب،
a year preceded by a score of the same,
مضى عام بنفس حال
so as in two decades before,
عقدين من الزمان،
we wiped our eyes,
مسحنا أعيننا،
laced caskets with flags,
وضعنا الأعلام على القبعات،
evacuated the crime scene of the club,
أخلينا مشهد الجريمة للنادي،
caterwauled in the street,
تشاجرنا في الشارع كالقطط،
laid our bodies on the concrete against the outlines of our fallen,
طرحنا أجسادنا على الخرسانة على حواف سقوطنا،
cried, "Of course we mattered,"
بكينا، "كنا ذوات قيمة،"
chanted for our disappeared.
شدونا لمفقودنا.
The women wept this year.
بكين النساء في هذا العام.
They did.
بكين حقاً.
In the same year, we were ready.
في نفس العام، كنا على أهبة الاستعداد.
The year we lost our inhibition and moved with courageous abandon
العام الذي فقدنا فيه كبتنا مضينا بهجرنا الجسور
was also the year we stared down barrels,
كان نفس العام الذي حملقنا فيه بماسورات البنادق،
sang of cranes in skies, ducked and parried,
قمنا بالغناء للرافعات في السماء تهبط وتتصدى،
caught gold in hijab, collected death threats,
أمسكنا ذهباً في الحجاب، وجمعنا تهديدات الموت،
knew ourselves as patriots,
وعرفنا أنفسنا كوطنيين،
said, "We're 35 now, time we settled down and found a running mate,"
قيل، "نحن 35 الآن، وقت أن استقر بنا الحال ووجدنا رفيق الهروب،
made road maps for infant joy, shamed nothing but fear,
صنعنا خرائط الطرق لمتعة طفولية، ما اعترانا عار إلا من الخوف،
called ourselves fat and meant, of course,
قلنا عن أنفسنا أننا بدينات، عن قصد، بالطبع،
impeccable.
ومعصومات من الخطأ.
This year, we were women,
هذا العام، كنا نساء،
not brides or trinkets,
لا عرائس ولا حلي،
not an off-brand gender,
ولا جنس غير معروف،
not a concession, but women.
ليس تنازلاً، فقط نساء.
Instruct your babies.
وجّهي صغارك.
Remind them that the year has passed to be docile or small.
ذكّريهم بأن عام التقزم والانصياع قد مضى.
Some of us said for the first time that we were women,
بعضنا قال لأول مرة أننا نساء،
took this oath of solidarity seriously.
وأخذن هذا العهد بالتعاضد بجدية.
Some of us bore children and some of us did not,
بعضنا ولدن أطفالا ولم تفعل الباقيات،
and none of us questioned whether that made us real
ولم تتساءل إحدانا إذا كان هذا يجعلنا واقعيات
or appropriate or true.
أو ملائمات أو نساء حقيقيات.
When she asks you of this year,
عندما تسألك ابنتك عن هذا العام،
your daughter, whether your offspring or heir to your triumph,
ابنتك، سواء كانت من ذريتك أو وريثتك
from her comforted side of history teetering towards woman,
من على جانبها المريح من التاريخ مترنحة في طريقها لتكون امرأة
she will wonder and ask voraciously,
ستتتعجب وتسأل بنَهَم،
though she cannot fathom your sacrifice,
رغم عجزها عن إدراك تضحيتك،
she will hold your estimation of it holy,
ستظل تحمل لها تقديراً مقدساً،
curiously probing, "Where were you?
وتسأل بفضول، "أين كنتِ؟"
Did you fight? Were you fearful or fearsome?
هل قاتلتِ؟ هل كنتِ خائفة أم مخيفة؟
What colored the walls of your regret?
ما لون جدران ندمك؟
What did you do for women in the year it was time?
ما الذي فعلتِه للنساء عندما حانت السنة؟
This path you made for me, which bones had to break?
لهذا الدرب الذي صنعتِه لي، أية عظام اضطررت لسحقها؟
Did you do enough, and are you OK, momma?
هل قمتِ بما فيه الكفاية، هل أنت بخير يا أمي؟
And are you a hero?"
وهل أنت بطلة؟"
She will ask the difficult questions.
ستسأل الأسئلة الصعبة.
She will not care about the arc of your brow,
لن تعبأ بتقويسة حاجبك،
the weight of your clutch.
ولا بثقل قبضتك.
She will not ask of your mentions.
لن تسأل عن ذكراك.
Your daughter, for whom you have already carried so much, wants to know
لابنتك والتي حملتِ لها الكثير تريد أنت تعرف
what you brought, what gift, what light did you keep from extinction?
ما الذي جلبتِه، ما الهدية والضوء الذي حافظتِ عليه من الاندثار؟
When they came for victims in the night,
عندما جاءوا للضحايا من الليل،
did you sleep through it or were you roused?
هل كنت نائمة أم يقظة؟
What was the cost of staying woke?
ماذا كان ثمن السهر؟
What, in the year we said time's up, what did you do with your privilege?
ماذا فعلت، في السنة التي قلنا فيها مضى الوقت، ماذا فعلت بميزتك؟
Did you sup on others' squalor?
هل ارتشفت قذارة الآخرين؟
Did you look away or directly into the flame?
هل أشحت بوجهك بعيداً أم واجهت اللهب؟
Did you know your skill or treat it like a liability?
هل أدركت ما لديك من مهارة أو تعاملت معها كعبء؟
Were you fooled by the epithets of "nasty" or "less than"?
هل غرتك النعوت "وضيعة" أم "أقل من"؟
Did you teach with an open heart or a clenched fist?
هل قمت بالتدريس بقلب رحب أم بقبضة مضمومة؟
Where were you?
أين كنت؟
Tell her the truth. Make it your life.
أخبريها بالحقيقة. اجعلي منها حياتك.
Confirm it. Say, "Daughter, I stood there
قومي بتأكيدها، " ابنتي، لقد وقفت هنا
with the moment drawn on my face like a dagger,
بتلك اللحظة مشهرة في وجهي كالخنجر،
and flung it back at itself,
قاذفة إياها على نفسها،
slicing space for you."
كي يخلو الحيز من أجلك؟"
Tell her the truth, how you lived in spite of crooked odds.
أخبريها بالحقيقة، كيف عشت بالرغم من قسوة الطريق.
Tell her you were brave,
أخبريها أنك كنت شجاعة،
and always, always in the company of courage,
ودائماً، دائماً كنت في صحبة الشجاعة،
mostly the days when you just had yourself.
حتى في معظم الأيام التي لم يكن عضدك سوى نفسك.
Tell her she was born as you were,
أخبريها أنها ولدت مثلما كنت،
as your mothers before, and the sisters beside them,
وكما الجدات من قبل بجانبهن أخواتهن،
in the age of legends, like always.
في عصر الأساطير، كما الحال دائماً
Tell her she was born just in time,
أخبريها أنها ولدت في التوقيت المثالي تماماً،
just in time
الوقت المثالي
to lead.
لتقود.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)